Emanuele Rossi

♥ Barcelona 🖾 emanuele.rossi1909@gmail.com 🔗 emanuelerossi.co.uk in emanuele-rossi 🗘 emalgorithm

Summary

I'm an ML researcher specializing in generative models for structural biology. Before jumping into MLxBio, my background combined **fundamental research** experience with real-world **product impact**. I'm the first author of Scalable Inception Graph Network , now **used in production by AirBnB**, and Temporal Graph Network , which has received over **750 Github stars**. While at Twitter, I successfully developed multiple ML models for the "who-to-follow" recommendation feature, resulting in an increase of over **1.2M follow actions daily**.

Education

Imperial College London

Oct 2020 - Feb 2024

Ph.D. in Computer Science - Supervisor: Prof. Michael Bronstein

- ∘ My research **∠** focused on solving the challenges preventing the success of **Graph Neural Networks** on real-world applications
- My work has been published at top conferences including ICML, ICLR, AAAI and RecSys

University of Cambridge

Oct 2018 - Jun 2019

Master in Advanced Computer Science – Supervisor: Prof. Pietro Liò

- Graduated with **Distinction** (4.0 GPA)
- Thesis: "Graph Deep Learning for ncRNA data" (published

 at KDD 2019 GDL workshop)

Imperial College London

Oct 2015 - Jun 2018

Bachelor in Computer Science

o Graduated with First Class Honors (4.0 GPA)

Experience

Machine Learning Researcher

NYC (remote)

VantAI

Twitter

Jan 2024 - Present

- Co-led development of Neo-1 ∠, a state-of-the-art all-atom latent diffusion model for multimodal structure prediction and de-novo biomolecule generation.
 - Model Design: Led the design and exploration of model architectures, diffusion formulations, and inference methods, establishing efficient experimentation workflows.
 - Large-scale Training: Managed distributed training across 100+ GPUs, optimizing computational resources and model performance.
 - **Data Engineering**: Contributed to the development of high-quality, leakage-free biomolecular datasets (see Plinder ♥, Pinder ♥) used to train the model.
 - Mentoring: Mentored and supervised 3 PhD interns who made substantial contributions to the project.
 - Cross-functional Collaboration: Partnered closely with computational biologists and chemists to assess and enhance model applicability and accuracy.

Machine Learning Researcher

London

Jun 2019 - Feb 2023

• Worked on applied and fundamental research around graph neural networks

- Scaled these technologies to graphs with tens of billions of edges
- Developed an embedding-based model to recommend users "who to follow", leading to an **increase of more than 1M follow actions** per day on the platform

Machine Learning Engineer

London

Fabula AI

Mar 2019 - Jun 2019

• Researched and developed novel graph deep learning models for fake news classification

o Fabula AI was acquired by Twitter in June 2019

Software Engineering Intern

Google

California Jul 2017 – Oct 2017

• Worked in the Google Play Store infrastructure team

Selected Publications

- E. Rossi et al. Temporal Graph Networks for Deep Learning on Dynamic Graphs. ICML 2020 GRL Workshop. arXiv:2006.10637 , blog . A new model for deep learning on dynamic graphs (¿300 citations, ¿700 Github stars). Adopted by memgraph (graph analytics company) and used by GraphCore to benchmark their hardware .
- ∘ E. Rossi*, F. Frasca* et al. SIGN: Scalable Inception Graph Neural Networks. ICML 2020 GRL Workshop. arXiv:2004.11198 , blog . First graph deep learning model to scale to graphs with billions of edges (¿200 citations). Used in production by Airbnb .
- ∘ B. Chamberlain, S. Shirobokov, E. Rossi et al. Graph Neural Networks for Link Prediction with Subgraph Sketching. ICLR 2022, Oral (top 5%). arXiv:2209.15486 ☑. First GNN model to scale link prediction to graphs with millions of nodes thanks to sketching, a hashing technique which enables efficient computation of subgraph statistics.
- o E. Rossi et al. On the Unreasonable Effectiveness of Feature propagation in Learning on Graphs with Missing Node Features. Learning on Graphs Conference 2022. arXiv:2111.12128 ₺, blog ₺. First model to enable scalable graph learning with partially missing node features.

Projects and Awards

LeadTheFuture

Jun 2018 - Mar 2023

 $Co ext{-}Founder$

- LeadTheFuture

 is a non-profit mentoring organization and the largest merit-based STEM community in Italy, with more than 200 mentors (engineers, researchers, and entrepreneurs) and 500 selected mentees
- Our work has been featured in Forbes 🗹

Talks and Blog Posts

∘ I have written a series of blog posts on my research (full list \mathbf{Z}) and have been invited to give over 10 talks (full list \mathbf{Z})